{"tossups": [{"question": "One man with this first name loaned Pennsylvania $3,000,000 to finance its civil war effort. That man was charged with selling more than a billion dollars' worth of bonds, but his (*)  financial empire collapsed after he failed to complete the Northern Pacific Railroad, thus precipitating the Panic of 1873. Another man with this first name, but not the nickname \"Diamond Jim\", attempted with his partner to corner the gold market, with disastrous results that caused another panic. That partner was James Fisk. One man with this last name signed an unpopular treaty with Great Britain and was the first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court. For ten points, name this first name of men named Cooke and Gould, and the last name of John, who co-wrote the Federalist Papers.", "answer": "Jay", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One leader of this country was the originator of the maxim \"theconstitution is just a piece of paper\". That man organized a crackdown on illegal loggers and established his country's largest national park at Yaque del Sur. One leader (*)  of this country attempted several times to have it annexed, and was opposed by the poet Salome Urena. Another leader of this country was overthrown in an American invasion after attempting to break up latifundia. That leader was Juan Bosch, and he       succeeded a man whose slogan was \"god and\" himself. That man also renamed the capital of this country after himself and perpetrated the Parsley Massacre. For ten points, name this country once led by Rafael Trujillo.", "answer": "Dominican Republic", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One leader of this country was the originator of the maxim \"theconstitution is just a piece of paper\". That man organized a crackdown on illegal loggers and established his country's largest national park at Yaque del Sur. One leader (*)  of this country attempted several times to have it annexed, and was opposed by the poet Salome Urena. Another leader of this country was overthrown in an American invasion after attempting to break up latifundia. That leader was Juan Bosch, and he       succeeded a man whose slogan was \"god and\" himself. That man also renamed the capital of this country after himself and perpetrated the Parsley Massacre. For ten points, name this country once led by Rafael Trujillo.", "answer": "Dominican Republic", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One man who nearly died in this manner was the son of a man referred to as \"Braginoco\" by the Portuguese mercenaries who were the proximate cause of that incident. Another (*)  man who died in this manner copied out nearly the entirety of  Medea and passed it off of a philosophical treatise. One man nicknamed for this process was contrasted via that nickname with Leucippus. King Nanda Bayin of Pegu was temporarily struck dumb after responding in this way to a comment that Venice was a kingdom without a King, and Chrysippus died while doing this in response to a drunken donkey's attempts to eat a fig. For ten points, name this action, part of the nickname of the theorist of the atom, Democritus, and part of the name of a Frans Hals painting of a cavalier.", "answer": "Laughing", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One man who nearly died in this manner was the son of a man referred to as \"Braginoco\" by the Portuguese mercenaries who were the proximate cause of that incident. Another (*)  man who died in this manner copied out nearly the entirety of  Medea and passed it off of a philosophical treatise. One man nicknamed for this process was contrasted via that nickname with Leucippus. King Nanda Bayin of Pegu was temporarily struck dumb after responding in this way to a comment that Venice was a kingdom without a King, and Chrysippus died while doing this in response to a drunken donkey's attempts to eat a fig. For ten points, name this action, part of the nickname of the theorist of the atom, Democritus, and part of the name of a Frans Hals painting of a cavalier.", "answer": "Laughing", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Allied Shawnee and Delaware Indians were defeated by the British at the Battle of Bushy Run near this modern-day city. A thermal inversion in 1948 exacerbated air pollution in Donora, a small town south of this city, and killed 20 people. This city's landmarks include PPG Place and Point State Park, which used to be (*)  a French fort.. Tax protesters marched on this city during the Whiskey Rebellion and gathered at Braddock's Field southeast of this city. Edith Wharton described the \"five lords\" of this city, which included Henry Frick and George      Westinghouse. The Homestead Strike occurred near, For ten points, this Pennsylvania \"Steel City\" at the confluence of the rivers Allegheny and Monongahela.", "answer": "Pittsburgh", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "According to his former secret service guard, this man's favorite Disneyland ride was one named after a river in his country. This man built the palace at Gbadolite, and this man mandated that all television broadcasts begin with (*)  his face descending from the clouds. This man sponsored a fight between Joe Frazier and Muhammad Ali and changed his name from Joseph to a Swahili phrase meaning \"the invincible warrior who goes from conquest to conquest leaving fire in his wake\". This man overthrew Patrice Lumumba and turned him over to Moise Tshombe's Katangese Government for execution. For ten points, name this longtime dictator of Zaire.", "answer": "Mobutu  Sese Seko", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "According to his former secret service guard, this man's favorite Disneyland ride was one named after a river in his country. This man built the palace at Gbadolite, and this man mandated that all television broadcasts begin with (*)  his face descending from the clouds. This man sponsored a fight between Joe Frazier and Muhammad Ali and changed his name from Joseph to a Swahili phrase meaning \"the invincible warrior who goes from conquest to conquest leaving fire in his wake\". This man overthrew Patrice Lumumba and turned him over to Moise Tshombe's Katangese Government for execution. For ten points, name this longtime dictator of Zaire.", "answer": "Mobutu  Sese Seko", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One leader of this country initiated \"Operation Drive out the Filth\". That leader urged conciliation toward his country's minorities in a speech in English, then added \"we will crush the snakes\" in his native language. This country (*)  was the site of guerrilla campaigns called  chimurengas, and one of the less violent leaders of this country's independence movement was Archbishop Abel Muzorewa. This country awarded the farms of its white community to \"war veterans\", then saw its agricultural productivity precipitously drop. Another independence leader in this country was Joshua Nkomo. For Ten Points, name this country currently led by Robert Mugabe.", "answer": "Zimbabwe", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One leader of this country initiated \"Operation Drive out the Filth\". That leader urged conciliation toward his country's minorities in a speech in English, then added \"we will crush the snakes\" in his native language. This country (*)  was the site of guerrilla campaigns called  chimurengas, and one of the less violent leaders of this country's independence movement was Archbishop Abel Muzorewa. This country awarded the farms of its white community to \"war veterans\", then saw its agricultural productivity precipitously drop. Another independence leader in this country was Joshua Nkomo. For Ten Points, name this country currently led by Robert Mugabe.", "answer": "Zimbabwe", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One unit whose \"Nazdar\" regiment had fought in France fought to takecontrol of this structure and established the Committee of Members of the Constituent Assembly. The original name of one of this structure's endpoints (*)  was Haishenwei, and the head of state responsible for building an offshoot of this structure said it would be built \"cleanly\", which many interpreted as a signal that prisoner labor would not be used. \"Green Ukraine\" declared its independence near the terminus of this structure, and during fighting along this structure, the Czech Legion captured a reserve of gold held by a government based in Omsk. For ten points, name this structure, the largest of its type, which runs from Moscow to Vladivostok.", "answer": "Trans-Siberian  railway", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One monarch of this name and number was styled \"the guided one\", despite losing control of his harem and disbanding his army. Another ruler of this name and number is the villain of a George Peele play in which Sebastian I of Portugal dies in an attempt to restore his throne. That play is (*)   The Battle of Alcazar. Another ruler failed to restore the authority of the Seljuks in Iraq, and another started a war in which his empire was destroyed by plucking out two envoys' beards. Another ruler of this name and number is titled \"Fatih\" due to his most famous action and held the throne by alternating with Murad II. For ten points, give this name and number shared by a Caliph of Cordoba, a Sultan of Morocco, and an Ottoman Sultan known for sacking Constantinople.", "answer": "Muhammad II  (prompt on \"Muhammad\" or \"Mehmed\", accept \" Mehmed II \")", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This chief justice heard a case in which the plaintiff said there were exceptionsto the mootness doctrine. That case was  DeFunis v. Odegaard. Part of a test developed under this justice says that the statute in question must entangle the government in religious affairs. That is part of his Lemon test. (*)  This chief justice heard a case in which the court of appeals upheld a district court decision to allow the creation of a desegregation plan. In one case, the Supreme Court under this man created the \"good faith exception\" in an amendment to  Mapp v. Ohio in  U.S. v. Leon. This chief justice who ruled in the  Swann decision was nominated by a president who thought justices should protect against \"criminal forces\" and decried the judicial activism of the Warren court. For 10 points, identify this conservative Chief Justice who was nominated by Nixon and succeed by William Rehnquist.", "answer": "Warren  Burger", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This modern-day country was first united by the Shabdrung, and it paid annuities to Britain for decades after losing the Duar War. This country was ruled for centuries by  desis and  je khenpos until a monarchy was declared by (*) King Ugyen. This country requires all citizens to wear its traditional loose robes, an issue for Hindu migrants living in its semi-tropical South. This country transitioned to democracy under King Jigme Namgyal Whangchuck, whose father coined the term \"gross national happiness\". This country's name comes from a Sanskrit word meaning \"land bordering Tibet\". For Ten Points, name this country with its capital at Thimphu.", "answer": "Kingdom of  Bhutan", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Linguistic evidence suggests that early Indo-Europeans traveled in warbands of this many people. Medieval Seoul had this many gates, six of which are still extant. One king of this regnal number won the battle of Las Navas de Tolosa, and another king of this regnal number was invited by his sister (*),  Isabella, to invade a nearby nation. This many people made up a group of Spanish modernist composers modeled on the Five and les Six, and this many \"banners\" were utilized in the Qing Army. Taoist belief centers on this many Immortals, and Buddhism uses this number of rules for Nuns and this number of core beliefs in their \"noble path\". For ten points, name this regnal number of a king who founded the Church of England and had six wives.", "answer": "8", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Linguistic evidence suggests that early Indo-Europeans traveled in warbands of this many people. Medieval Seoul had this many gates, six of which are still extant. One king of this regnal number won the battle of Las Navas de Tolosa, and another king of this regnal number was invited by his sister (*),  Isabella, to invade a nearby nation. This many people made up a group of Spanish modernist composers modeled on the Five and les Six, and this many \"banners\" were utilized in the Qing Army. Taoist belief centers on this many Immortals, and Buddhism uses this number of rules for Nuns and this number of core beliefs in their \"noble path\". For ten points, name this regnal number of a king who founded the Church of England and had six wives.", "answer": "8", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The most famous landmark of this island was replaced with a statue of a stag and a fawn. A set of maritime laws of the Byzantine Empire were named for this island. One native of this island wrote an epic poem about the adventures of Jason, and (*)  George Frapan coordinated the more successful of the two Ottoman sieges of this island. The defender in that siege was Pierre Villiers de l'Isle Adam, the grand master of the Knights Hospitaller. This island's most famous landmark probably had its legs together, rather than spread as it is usually depicted, due to the lack of sophisticated bronze-casting techniques at the time. For ten points, name this island, home to a famous statue of Helios.", "answer": "Rhodes", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The most famous landmark of this island was replaced with a statue of a stag and a fawn. A set of maritime laws of the Byzantine Empire were named for this island. One native of this island wrote an epic poem about the adventures of Jason, and (*)  George Frapan coordinated the more successful of the two Ottoman sieges of this island. The defender in that siege was Pierre Villiers de l'Isle Adam, the grand master of the Knights Hospitaller. This island's most famous landmark probably had its legs together, rather than spread as it is usually depicted, due to the lack of sophisticated bronze-casting techniques at the time. For ten points, name this island, home to a famous statue of Helios.", "answer": "Rhodes", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This dynasty launched an invasion under Gen. Ban Chao in which itcaptured the cities of Kucha and Kara Shahr. One emperor of this dynasty was restored to the throne by the Greenwood Rebels. Another military (*)  campaign under this dynasty was a disastrous attack under General Li Ling, who defected to the Barbarian tribe he was attacking. This dynasty was interrupted by a succession crisis caused by Emperor Ai's homosexuality. That interruption was ended by Red Eyebrow rebels. That was the Xin Dynasty, founded by Wang Mang. The Yellow Turban rebellion fatally weakened, --for ten points-- this Chinese dynasty that succeeded the Qin and preceded the Era of the Three Kingdoms.", "answer": "Han", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This dynasty launched an invasion under Gen. Ban Chao in which itcaptured the cities of Kucha and Kara Shahr. One emperor of this dynasty was restored to the throne by the Greenwood Rebels. Another military (*)  campaign under this dynasty was a disastrous attack under General Li Ling, who defected to the Barbarian tribe he was attacking. This dynasty was interrupted by a succession crisis caused by Emperor Ai's homosexuality. That interruption was ended by Red Eyebrow rebels. That was the Xin Dynasty, founded by Wang Mang. The Yellow Turban rebellion fatally weakened, --for ten points-- this Chinese dynasty that succeeded the Qin and preceded the Era of the Three Kingdoms.", "answer": "Han", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One ruler of this dynasty faced a revolt under Mstivoj after losing the Battle of Stilo. The only male and the only female holders of this dynasty's highest title to be canonized were from this dynasty, which eventually suppressed the  (*) Slawenaufstand. Land grants that this dynasty's most famous ruler gave to Margrave Gero led to a rebellion by his half brother, Thankmar. It's not the Carolingians, but during this dynasty's rule, their realm underwent a namesake \"renaissance\". The first emperor from this dynasty was Henry the Fowler, whose son defeated Bulcsu harka. For ten points, name this Imperial dynasty whose namesake defeated the Magyars at the Battle of Lechfeld.", "answer": "Ottonian", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One ruler of this polity was the former slave Malik Kafur, who attempted to convert this polity to his own religion and was swiftly overthrown. Another ruler of this polity employed the poet (*) Amir Khusrau, and yet another ruler, Iltumish, appointed his daughter Raziya as his heir. This polity's ruling dynasties included the Burji and Khilji, and rulers of this polity including Balban were former slave soldiers known as  ghulams. This polity briefly moved its capital to Daulatabad, and its final period of expansion occurred under Sultan Sikandar Lodi, one of whose descendants lost the First Battle of Panipat. For ten points, name this polity named for a North Indian city.", "answer": "Delhi  Sultanate", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One ruler of this polity was the former slave Malik Kafur, who attempted to convert this polity to his own religion and was swiftly overthrown. Another ruler of this polity employed the poet (*) Amir Khusrau, and yet another ruler, Iltumish, appointed his daughter Raziya as his heir. This polity's ruling dynasties included the Burji and Khilji, and rulers of this polity including Balban were former slave soldiers known as  ghulams. This polity briefly moved its capital to Daulatabad, and its final period of expansion occurred under Sultan Sikandar Lodi, one of whose descendants lost the First Battle of Panipat. For ten points, name this polity named for a North Indian city.", "answer": "Delhi  Sultanate", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Sources from this empire speak of being raided by a people called the Ahhiyawa, which may be identifiable with the Greek Achaians. One ruler of this empire suffered from epilepsy, and this empire was bordered by states established by the (*)  Luwians. This empire may have also fallen due to raids from the Caucasus, or as part of an earthquake storm in the fatal year of 1277 BCE. This empire was the first to fall to the \"Sea People\", and one of its rulers fought a battle commemorated at Abu Simbel. This empire was headquartered at the city of Hattusa. For Ten Points, name this empire that fought the Egyptians at the Battle of Kadesh.", "answer": "Hittite", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Sources from this empire speak of being raided by a people called the Ahhiyawa, which may be identifiable with the Greek Achaians. One ruler of this empire suffered from epilepsy, and this empire was bordered by states established by the (*)  Luwians. This empire may have also fallen due to raids from the Caucasus, or as part of an earthquake storm in the fatal year of 1277 BCE. This empire was the first to fall to the \"Sea People\", and one of its rulers fought a battle commemorated at Abu Simbel. This empire was headquartered at the city of Hattusa. For Ten Points, name this empire that fought the Egyptians at the Battle of Kadesh.", "answer": "Hittite", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A group of maroons in this country speak the Saramaccanlanguage, which is tonal despite being sourced from English. Those people escaped during an uprising that overthrew Gov. Francis Willoughby, after whom this country was briefly named. This country's (*)  current president leads the \"Megacombination\" and has been convicted in absentia for cocaine trafficking. That      president is Desi Bouterse. Along with its Western neighbor, this country is the only non-majority-Christian one on its continent due to the importation of labor from Indonesia during this country's colonial period. The inhabitants of this country speak Sranan Tongo. For ten points, name this country formerly known as Dutch Guiana.", "answer": "Suriname", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A group of maroons in this country speak the Saramaccanlanguage, which is tonal despite being sourced from English. Those people escaped during an uprising that overthrew Gov. Francis Willoughby, after whom this country was briefly named. This country's (*)  current president leads the \"Megacombination\" and has been convicted in absentia for cocaine trafficking. That      president is Desi Bouterse. Along with its Western neighbor, this country is the only non-majority-Christian one on its continent due to the importation of labor from Indonesia during this country's colonial period. The inhabitants of this country speak Sranan Tongo. For ten points, name this country formerly known as Dutch Guiana.", "answer": "Suriname", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One legend about this empire's origins speaks of how its ruler fled the capital in terror before a siege while his son remained and defeated the besiegers. One of the final rulers of this empire dreamt of thousands of foreigners (*)  on an empty battlefield just before his death, which precipitated a civil war between his two sons. Descendants of this empire's royalty included Garcilaso de la Vega, and this empire was sometimes named for the four administrative  suyus that it was divided into. The Lord of Cajamarca was a major power broker in this empire, as was the Lord of Quito. For ten points, name this empire that ruled much of Western South America in pre-Columbian times.", "answer": "Inca  (accept  Tawantinsuyu  or \"Empire of the four Quarters\" before \"suyu\")", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One legend about this empire's origins speaks of how its ruler fled the capital in terror before a siege while his son remained and defeated the besiegers. One of the final rulers of this empire dreamt of thousands of foreigners (*)  on an empty battlefield just before his death, which precipitated a civil war between his two sons. Descendants of this empire's royalty included Garcilaso de la Vega, and this empire was sometimes named for the four administrative  suyus that it was divided into. The Lord of Cajamarca was a major power broker in this empire, as was the Lord of Quito. For ten points, name this empire that ruled much of Western South America in pre-Columbian times.", "answer": "Inca  (accept  Tawantinsuyu  or \"Empire of the four Quarters\" before \"suyu\")", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "El General was a leading figure in the early stages of this event. In one country, this event preceded an electoral defeat by Ahmed Shafik, the Vice President of an unpopular former leader. This event began in another country when two teenagers (*)  were tortured after doing graffiti in the town of Deraa. This event brought the Tamarod and Ennahda Parties into power. Two public squares in two different countries with the same name were both used in protests during this event. In one of those countries, this event brought Abbo Rab Mansur Hadi to power. For 10       points, name this event that began when the vegetable vendor Mohamed Bouazizi set himself on fire in Tunisia", "answer": "Arab Spring", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "El General was a leading figure in the early stages of this event. In one country, this event preceded an electoral defeat by Ahmed Shafik, the Vice President of an unpopular former leader. This event began in another country when two teenagers (*)  were tortured after doing graffiti in the town of Deraa. This event brought the Tamarod and Ennahda Parties into power. Two public squares in two different countries with the same name were both used in protests during this event. In one of those countries, this event brought Abbo Rab Mansur Hadi to power. For 10       points, name this event that began when the vegetable vendor Mohamed Bouazizi set himself on fire in Tunisia", "answer": "Arab Spring", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In a biography titled The Founder, Robert I. Rotberg inferred that this man might have been in a homosexual relationship with Neville Pickering. Polish princess Radziwi\u0142\u0142 had an unhealthy obsession with this man, and falsely claimed that she was engaged to this man. Charles Rudd and this man convinced King (*) Lobengula to hand over the resource-rich Matebeland; this was known as the \"Rudd Concession.\" While he enjoyed a successful life, this man disastrously supported the \"Jameson Raid\" on a republic lead by Paul Kruger, and he never ended up realizing his dream of building a railroad from Cape Town to Cairo. De Beers Consolidated Mines was founded by \u00c2\u2013 for ten points \u00c2\u2013 what diamond magnate and \"colossal\" British imperialist, the namesake of a prestigious Oxford scholarship?", "answer": "Cecil  Rhodes", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In a biography titled The Founder, Robert I. Rotberg inferred that this man might have been in a homosexual relationship with Neville Pickering. Polish princess Radziwi\u0142\u0142 had an unhealthy obsession with this man, and falsely claimed that she was engaged to this man. Charles Rudd and this man convinced King (*) Lobengula to hand over the resource-rich Matebeland; this was known as the \"Rudd Concession.\" While he enjoyed a successful life, this man disastrously supported the \"Jameson Raid\" on a republic lead by Paul Kruger, and he never ended up realizing his dream of building a railroad from Cape Town to Cairo. De Beers Consolidated Mines was founded by \u00c2\u2013 for ten points \u00c2\u2013 what diamond magnate and \"colossal\" British imperialist, the namesake of a prestigious Oxford scholarship?", "answer": "Cecil  Rhodes", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}